Boker tov.
Alright, today's דף daf *daf* is ק"ג *kuf gimmel* 103.
And we start with the very bottom of ק"ב עמוד ב' Kof-Bet
Amud Bet *kuf bet amud bet*. And we're in the middle of
a debate of רב Rav *Rav* and שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* about the
scope of מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish. *makeh b'patish* as opposed to the
scope of בונה Boneh. *boneh*, where רב Rav, *Rav* has a pretty
broad definition of בונה Boneh, *boneh* to even includes כלים keilim, *keilim*,
like making a shovel from scratch. שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* has a very
narrow definition of בונה Boneh *boneh*; he won't even include like carving
a stone, you know, or chiseling a stone or a hole in
a chicken coop, but for him he broadens a very big definition
of מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish. *makeh b'patish*.
Somebody asked me at the end of yesterday, so for רב Rav,
*Rav* if even making a כלי Kli *kli* is בונה Boneh *boneh*,
what would be a מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish. *makeh b'patish*? But מכה
בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *makeh b'patish* could be, for example, the vessel's already
made and you're just doing some final like engraving on the vessel.
מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *makeh b'patish* is often conceived of as like
the last act in the making of an object, even if the
object was usable and sort of existed beforehand. So, but it seems
that רב Rav *Rav* wants to put things into the בונה Boneh
*boneh* category, not מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *makeh b'patish*. And the flip
side of that is that he would have בונה Boneh בכלים *boneh
b'keilim*, right? There's a whole debate whether there's a concept of בניין
*binyan* by vessels. רב Rav *Rav* says there is, and then the
ראשונים Rishonim *rishonim* debate what exactly is the scope of that. Maybe
it's only when you make something new, like you had an unmade
shovel and you made it into a shovel, as opposed to something
that normally is taken apart or put together. Maybe it's only if
it's a very sort of tight fit or screwed in, but at
some degree רב Rav *Rav* would call something בניין *binyan*, בונה Boneh,
*boneh* even by כלים *keilim*. I want to say one other thing
about מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *makeh b'patish* before we continue on. So,
besides the debate of רב Rav *Rav* and שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* whether
to apply it narrowly or broadly, normally as I said, in the
משנה Mishnah? *mishnah* you could have assumed מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *makeh
b'patish* was part of בונה Boneh, *boneh*; it's part of the process
of building, you're banging on the hammer and you're making things and
so on, maybe a stage in the process even though it's not
yet complete. But again the גמרא Gemara *gemara* really abstracts it more
to this more generic category. But when we do abstract it to
the more generic category, we tend to define it as I said,
like doing the final act of making something. But if you look
at רש"י Rashi *Rashi* in the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says something slightly different, which is not to exclude the other definition,
but if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi* in the משנה Mishnah,
*mishnah* by מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish. *makeh b'patish*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
the following. It's the last wide line from the top of the
page, like four lines from the bottom. המכה בפטיש ha'Makeh B'Patish. *hamakeh
b'patish*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, גם הוא באבות מלאכות melachot. *gam hu
b'avot melachot*. והוא בלע"ז *vehu b'la'az* pique, I don't know what that
is, המפוצץ את האבן *hamifotzetz et ha'even*, you break out the stone
מן הסלע *min hasela* from the, you know, from the quarry, לאחר
שחצב את האבן סביב *le'achar shechatzav et ha'even saviv*, you've totally sort
of carved it out all around, ומפרידה מן ההר קצת *umafriydah min
hahar ktzat*, and it's basically it's pretty much like mostly removed from
the mountain, it's mostly carved out, והוא מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish מכה
גדולה *vehu makeh b'patish makah gedolah*, you hit with a hammer, a
big bang, והיא מתפרקת *vehi mitpareket*, and then the whole stone comes
out, ונופלת *venofelet*. Now you would have said that's now let's see
how he conceptualizes it. וזהו גמר מלאכה Gmar melacha, של חוצבי האבן
*vezehu gmar melacha shel chotzvei ha'even*. This is the last step of
the process of the stonehewers. וכל הגומר בשבת מלאכה melacha *vechol hagomer
b'shabbat melacha*, תולדת מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish. *toldat makeh b'patish*, and anyone
who finishes an act is מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *makeh b'patish*. So
what's different about רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* is he does not say this
is the last act of making the stone, right? There's more to
be done from the stone's perspective, but it is the last step
of the process of this profession, of
stonehewers. The last thing the stonehewer does is they give it a
big bang. Then you call in other people. Then you call in
I don't know, the carvers or the engravers or whoever you call
it. So for רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, it's also important because it's part
of a step in a process. It is not necessarily the finishing
of the object. And if you look at תוספות Tosafot: *Tosafot*, תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* doesn't like it. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says,
one minute,
so first he doesn't like it because they didn't have making stones
in the משכן Mishkan *mishkan*. And he says, אלא נראה לריב"א *ela
nir'eh l'riva* תוספות Tosafot מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish *Tosafot makeh b'patish*, like
about four lines, three lines in it. דהיינו dehaynu מכה בפטיש Makeh
B'Patish? היינו מכוש אחרון שמכה על הכלי בשעת גמר מלאכה gmar melacha.
*dehaynu makeh b'patish haynu makosh acharon shemakeh al hakli b'sha'at gmar melacha*,
which is normally how it's defined is the finishing of the vessel,
the last bang. But the reason I point out רש"י Rashi *Rashi*,
it's more consistent with the sense of the משנה Mishnah, *mishnah* that
a מלאכה melacha. *melacha* can be not only the finishing of the
object, but a process in the stage of making the object. ורמב"ם
*veRambam* has that as well. For example, we're going to find out
later that immersing your clothes in water is considered מלבן *melaben*, is
considered laundering. Now why is it laundering? I mean, it's not the
end of the process. So maybe you could say some clothes if
you do immerse them in water that cleans them. Anyway, רמב"ם Rambam
*veRambam* says, because that's one of the stages of the process of
laundering. So can we imagine a מלאכה melacha. *melacha* that is not
actually constructive in itself, but that is part of a constructive process
and one stage along the way? That's what מכה בפטיש Makeh B'Patish.
*makeh b'patish* sounds like in the משנה Mishna, *mishnah*, even when we
change it. It's interesting that רש"י Rashi *Rashi* emphasizes it that's the
final stage of a process even if it's not the final stage
of an object. not the final stage of the working of the
object itself. Anyway so those are some ideas around מכה בפטיש maka
b'patish and now we continue from the bottom of ק"ב עמוד amud
ב and here we have the following. בעי מיניה, Ba'ei Minei, four
lines from the bottom. בעי מיניה רב נתן בר אושעיא מרבי יוחנן.
Ba'ei Minei Rav Natan Bar Oshaya Me'Rabbi Yochanan. So רב נתן בר
אושעיא Rav Natan Bar Oshaya asked of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. מסתת
משום מאי חייב? Mesatet mishum mai chayav? So the person that is
doing the like carving of the stone, like making maybe the smoothing
it or making the edge around it, what is the חיוב chiyuv
for because it's listed in the משנה? Mishna You certainly assume in
the משנה Mishna it's בונה. Boneh. It says בונה, Boneh מסתת, Mesatet,
and then מכה בפטיש. maka b'patish
So what is it חייב chayav for? ואחוי ליה בידיה משום מכה
בפטיש. Ve'achvei lei b'yadei mishum Makeh B'Patish.
He demonstrated with his hands because מכה בפטיש. maka b'patish Maybe he
did a little hammer blow, you know, signal or something. So anyway
rather than actually verbally answer. So he didn't like that answer. He
says or
רש"י Rashi says that he banged with his fist or something. Anyway
מכה בפטיש. maka b'patish So he says והנן תנן המסתת והמכה בפטיש.
Ve'hanan tnan: ha'mesatet ve'ha'makeh b'patish. We say מסתת mesatet and מכה בפטיש
maka b'patish. which seems to be that מסתת mesatet comes earlier, comes
in the בונה Boneh category. אימא Eima the מסתת mesatet is המכה
בפטיש. Okay so again we have a similar approach to שמואל, Shmuel,
which is wants בונה Boneh to be really fully constructing something and
things that are more like smaller scale, not fully making a type
of a you know of of a you know of a like
structure, like the carving the stone, making a making a shovel, those
types of things, more put those into the מכה בפטיש maka b'patish
category. Yes.
But you just said implied that מכה בפטיש maka b'patish might have
to involve some sort of a כלי Kli. where בונה Boneh clearly
doesn't.
Well right, I mean but מכה בפטיש maka b'patish is very generic,
meaning I would say it's the other way. According to שמואל, Shmuel
בונה Boneh might be limited to structures, meaning מכה בפטיש maka b'patish,
is much more broader. Now normally if you're dealing with a structure
you could be בונה, Boneh but for example we had the case
of making a hole in a chicken coop which שמואל Shmuel, thought
that wasn't significant enough to be בונה, boneh so he put it
in מכה בפטיש.
makke b'patish, You're saying מכה בפטיש makkeh bepatish. you have to be
using a כלי. Kli.
Oh, using a כלי. Kli. That's interesting.
Normally we don't, that's not normally when it's abstracted said as part
of the definition. It's usually said that it's the last act in
making something.
So I don't know, like for example some people say let's say
you
have I don't know like when you get if you have a
book and the pages haven't been cut and separated and you cut
the pages on שבת, Shabbat, right, so what מלאכה melacha is it?
So
some people want to say that's מכה בפטיש. That's not with a
כלי. Kli. You know normally it's not defined as specifically with the
emphasis on כלי. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא
שמע, Ta shma, come and hear. הקודח כל שהוא חייב. Ha'kodeach kol
shehu chayav.
If you make even a small hole you're חייב, chayav, and presumably
it's not even a hole all the way through.
And רש"י says קודח kodeach also implies that if you made a
hole all the way through, it would, you would call it נוקב
nokev if you wanted something to remain a hole. קודח Kodeach means
you make a hole to be filled, like making a hole and
then you're going to put a nail in it or a screw
in it. Okay so even a small amount. So what type of
a חיוב chiyuv is that? בשלמא לרב, Bishlama l'Rav, מחזי כמאן דחרחר
חורתא לבניינא. mechzei ke'man de'charachar churtah l'vinyana. For רב Rav, it makes
sense that it's בונה. boneh It looks like one making a hole
for a structure, which is interesting. What do you mean looks like?
We're trying to talk about a biblical מלאכה. melacha? But meaning it's
in that category. That's part of what בונה boneh is. So you
didn't make a whole structure, but it's part of the בונה boneh
types of acts. You make holes in your walls that you're going
to put in a nail and hang up a picture or something
like that. So again for רב, בונה boneh includes all of those
acts around בנין. binyan. אלא לשמואל, Ela l'Shmuel, לאו גמר מלאכה הוא.
lav gmar melacha hu. But for שמואל, Shmuel and here the גמרא
Gemara is very important because it's here where the גמרא Gemara abstracts
what שמואל Shmuel, has been saying. מכה בפטיש is broad for שמואל,
Shmuel. so what does מכה בפטיש mean? גמר מלאכה, melacha, the ending
of the מלאכה. melacha Meaning you have now somehow completed the act
or completed the object or according to what רש"י said in the
משנה, Mishna you've completed the process. But anyway this is not a
completion. You're making a hole that then the object isn't complete, the
process isn't complete, you're going to fill it with a nail. So
how can this be מכה בפטיש? And presumably it can't be בונה
boneh. because שמואל Shmuel. needs בונה boneh to be much more significant.
So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha b'mai askinnan, what
are we talking about here? דבזעיה ברמצא דפרזלא, De'vazya b'ramtza de'farzla, you
made the hole with like a with like an iron peg,
ושבקה בגוויה ve'shavka b'gavei and you left the peg in the hole.
היינו גמר מלאכה. Heinu gmar melacha. Now you're done. So you needed
to put up a peg to hang a picture or something, so
you took the peg, you banged you stuck it in the wall,
so now you made the hole with the peg and that's the
גמר מלאכה. melacha? And that's how come you're חייב chayav for מכה
בפטיש. But again what the גמרא Gemara is... so okay it's obviously
a little bit of a squeeze in that read of the משנה,
Mishna but it's important to understand that there's a really fundamental debate
here about the line between these two מלאכות. melachos For רב, בונה
boneh, does not have to be limited to a structure, it even
applies to vessels. Be it does not have to be you've completed
something, you've just carved the stone, you've made a hole in the
wall, you've... done some type of a change that is part of
the process of construction. Okay, so a very big category. So, and,
so what's מכה בפטיש for רב is not so clear like I
said, maybe it would be a case where it's on a vessel
and it's not even making the vessel, it's just doing some carving
on the vessel but for רב בונה boneh, is very big. שמואל,
Shmuel בונה boneh. really seems to be you've made a complete structure.
So it's A presumably limited to a structure, not כלים, not so
clear, but B also it's a real major transformation, you've really made
something fully. So therefore for him all these other things fall in
the מכה בפטיש category and the גמרא Gemara points out that you
leave a gap for שמואל. Shmuel. Because if you're not constructing a
full structure and you're doing something on a vessel or you're doing
something that's a part of a process and so on and it's
not complete, it's in the middle, it's neither בונה nor מכה בפטיש
if מכה בפטיש is about completing it. And the גמרא Gemara basically
says that's true, you would have that gap according to שמואל. Shmuel
And you made a hole in the wall, for רב it would
be בונה because it's part of a process of building and you've
made partial change towards doing something, and according to שמואל it's neither
בונה nor מכה בפטיש. Okay, so that is a very big debate
and it's important also because other practical cases could be dependent on
this debate of רב and שמואל. Okay, so now we move on
after having said that big issue, דהיינו so now זה הכלל, zeh
haklal, this is the general principle says the משנה, mishna. anything that
is a מלאכה melacha and it's מתקיים בשבת. mitkayem b'Shabbos. Now when
we read this yesterday I mentioned that מתקיים, mitkayem, the normal sense
of מתקיים mitkayem means it's permanent not temporary. But there's another aspect
of מתקיים mitkayem which actually רש"י said in the משנה mishnah: that
the גמרא Gemara will address it, I should have mentioned, which also
refers to the first point of the משנה mishna about the minimum
amount. That מתקיים mitkayem doesn't just mean it will last, but it
means like it's like it's it's a minimum amount of significance, it's
like there's some sense that you're done. You're done with at least
this stage. It's not like you've done something that isn't even complete.
And if you read רש"י on the משנה Mishnah says מתקיים, mitkayem,
I'll just read רש"י, שיש מתקיימת כיוצא בו ואין מוסיף עליה. she'yesh
mitkayemet k'yotzei bo v'ein mosif aleha.
Sometimes people leave something at this stage without adding to it. So
in a way it's another definition of a minimum amount. It's there's
some sense that you've done something of significance. Okay, so let's take
a look at how what the גמרא Gemara says. זה הכלל לאתויי
מאי, zeh haklal l'atuyei mai, what's that including? לאתויי דחק כפיזא בכפיא,
l'atuyei d'chak kafiza b'kapya, that you made a
like a what do you call it like containers in a type
of a in a type of a mold. So the way רש"י
says it is you carved out let's say quart volumes in some
type of a mold, even though some people might not leave it
at quarts, might break down the middle walls and make it into
a gallon container, but you but some people do keep it at
the quart size, so therefore you're done at this stage, even though
some people would see it as an interim stage, you're done at
this stage and therefore that is enough. So again the point being
here of מתקיים mitkayem is also that there's a sense of you
could be considered to be done here and not that you're still
incomplete. Okay, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר המכה
בקורנס על הסדן. omer hamakeh b'kurnas al hasadan. Now if we were
discussing מכה בפטיש could be a step in the process without completing
it, certainly it sounds that way according to רב, according to רש"י
in the משנה Mishnah that you you know it's the end of
the of the ewers even if you haven't started you know even
though there's more to be done with the stone, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel goes even further and he doesn't even
talk about changing an object. He just talks about a
stage in the process an act done in the process of building
even without having changed something. You're just banging your hammer on the
anvil, right? That's a normal thing somebody does. So as opposed to
making another hole in a stone where maybe the stone isn't complete
but it's getting there, here you're just doing one of the acts
that gets done in construction that hasn't even done any change. And
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you're still חייב.
chayav. המכה בקורנס על הסדן, hamakeh b'kurnas al hasadan, even that act
is considered part of בונה. So the גמרא Gemara really challenges this,
מאי קעביד? mai ka'avid? What are you doing with that act? You
haven't actually effected any change at all. Not only has it not
been completed, it's no change. So the גמרא Gemara says רבה ורב
יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbah v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarveihu, רבה Rabbah and רב
יוסף Rav Yosef both say, מפני שמאמן את ידו, mipnei she'me'amen et
yado, because you are getting your hand, you you know you're training
your hand by banging on it you're getting your hand in a
better sort of you know rhythm to now do the banging on
the nail, let's say you bang here and then you bang on
the nail, you bang whatever you do, however why ever you bang
on that anvil, so that helps you in the next act you're
going to do. Okay that helps you in the process and it's
preparing you for actually doing something of significance. So the גמרא Gemara
says really? That's מלאכה? melacha, So the גמרא Gemara says קשו בה
בני רחבה, kashu bah b'nei Rechava, so the בני רחבה, b'nei Rechava,
the sons of רחבה Rechava asked, אלא מעתה חזו ואומנו בשבתא, ela
me'ata chazu v'umnu b'shabta, let's say you go and you watch a
craftsman on שבתא. shabta. You know you go watch a TV show
on שבתא shabta that shows you how to how to bang nails,
this old house or whatever it is.
Anyway וגמר, v'gamar, and you learned how to do it by watching.
הכי נמי דמיחייב? hachi nami d'michayiv? Would you say you're חייב? chayav?
What? Learning a trade learning something. the intellectual knowledge is enough? Now
you could say watching is different, you're actually, it's something more physical,
your hand is getting
more able to do the act, but still the point is it's
all preparatory, it's not actually a מלאכה, melacha. so what type of
a מלאכה melacha. is that? One minute, let's see what the גמרא's
Gemara answer is. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אביי ורבא דאמרי
תרווייהו, ela Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarvaihu, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava both
say שכן מרדדי טסי משכן עושים כן. sheken meradedey tasey Mishkan osim
ken. This is what they would do in the משכן Mishkan when
they would make the gold plates for the beams, they would bang
the hammer first on the anvil, and then they would bang it
on the gold that they were thinning out and because if they
wouldn't do that, somehow the gold would have broken. Okay, gets the
hammer smooth, and that's a necessary part of banging out the gold.
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר אף המכה בקורנס על הסדן בשעת מלאכה חייב שכן מרדדי
טסי משכן עושים כן, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer af hamakeh b'kurnas
al hasadan b'sha'at melacha chayav sheken meradedey tasey Mishkan osim ken, even
banging on the anvil at the time of the work he is
liable, for those that did it in the משכן Mishkan, that thinned
out the gold did that. Now how does that answer it? It's
still the question, what are you doing, what are you accomplishing? So
the גמרא's Gemara answer might be, you know what, you're right, but
the same way maybe you're not accomplishing anything, but maybe the same
way we had like carrying and all these weird examples of carrying
which are just because that's how it was done in the משכן,
Mishkan maybe here too it's something that was done in the משכן
Mishkan. even if it's not productive, only specifically this and therefore it's
very much limited to the banging on the anvil and wouldn't extend
to anything else, it's just a unique type of a thing that
was done in the משכן. Mishkan. Although of course it seems better
to say that it's not just totally arbitrary, that what it's actually
saying is similar to what I said before, that you cannot bang
on the gold well, it would ruin the gold, if you had
not preceded it by banging on here, so it wasn't just abstractly
learning the skill, going to medical school. It's in the very act
of banging on the gold, right, that would have not succeeded had
you not started by alternating it with the banging on the anvil.
The problem still is with that, even though admittedly okay it's not
just learning, it's part of the process, let's say you never wound
up banging on the gold. You banged on the anvil and then
you stopped. Would you have done a מלאכה? melacha If you didn't
actually finish in effecting some change. And it sounds like רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says yes, that it's possible to
have a מלאכה melacha that is something that is part of a
process even if it has not yet effected a change. Now again
that's different than as I said the מכה בפטיש or the רמב"ם
Rambam for example that you put the clothes in water is part
of the process of laundering, there you might not have finished the
process but at least something has changed, the clothes are soaking wet,
you've banged on the stone. Here you haven't changed the object at
all and even so this thing that's part of that process even
before doing any change is still considered a מלאכה, melacha. so that's
certainly a big חידוש. chiddush. We don't rule like רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, but again this whole discussion of מכה
בפטיש and מכה על הסדן maka al hasadan is very interesting because
we're always told that שבת מלאכה Shabbos melacha is creating something. And
here you see it might be a stage in the process even
before it's complete and might emphasize more the types of activities that
are done in this profession even without emphasizing the change that has
yet occurred and certainly from רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel that no change has occurred. There were some questions. Yes. Exercising,
wouldn't that be permitted on שבת? Shabbos? Well
exercising no, again this is not, even according to רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel that exercising is not part of a
process of doing some type of a craft.
If you're preparing to have more strength?
Yeah yeah, but this was only even in the הוה אמינא hava
amina that was only when it was getting you the skills to
do some other thing that was a מלאכה. melacha Okay, exercise doesn't
give you the skills to do a particular מלאכה. melacha Exercise is
a different issue about sweating on שבת Shabbos and okay but that
and then if for health reasons and so on, so exercise in
some cases is okay, in some cases not, but it's certainly not
in this מלאכה melacha, category. Yes.
I'm curious, are they really concerned with the job or how a
human being would react? If someone says I'm just putting my clothes
in, he might say put some dye into the same tub. I
think we're dealing with more or less how people will react to
this מלאכה melacha as opposed to...
Well I think you are right that there is a social context
to this, right, it's not objective because what's defined as a certain
part of a process only takes place within a certain social context.
That's certainly true. Do you have a question?
No. Okay, alright, so let's now move on to the next משנה.
Mishnah Okay, so that was בונה and מכה בפטיש, two small little
מלאכות melachos, we all covered that in less than one page. Now
we move on to a whole other set of מלאכות, melachot, okay,
it's so funny like I told you like we had fifty דף
on carrying and like a half of an עמוד on every other
מלאכה. melacha Let's take a look,
if that much. החורש כל שהוא, hachoresh kol shehu, if you make
even the smallest. Now the emphasis here is on the size, right?
What is the minimum size? So חרישה charisha which is a furrow
in the ground for the sake of planting, even the smallest amount.
המנכש hamenakesh which is a weeding, removing weeds,
והמקרסם v'hamikarsam which is removing dried up
branches, והמזרד, v'hamizared, רש"י says it's also removing branches except that they're
moist branches, but all of is things done to encourage growth, to
cultivate growth, so those are interestingly not a תולדה toladah of חורש,
choreish, that's a תולדה toladah of זורע zoreya because it's encouraging growth,
although it's related in the sense
that these are all things done. חורש choreish also is part of
the process of allowing something to grow. Anyway,
מנכש menakeshe might be, by the way, מנכש menakeshe which is done
on the ground might be חורש choreish if it's done before you
plant. After you plant it might be זורע. zoreya. Anyway, so some
of these there's a little question of a line between חורש choreish
and זורע. zoreya. But presumably the last three are זורע zoreya because
they are or because they're encouraging the growth. All of those also
כל שהוא חייב, kol shehu chayav, even the smallest amount. So things
that are about חורש choreish and זורע zoreya going back to the
first two מלאכות, melachot. like we did some at the end, carrying
בונה, מכה בפטיש, now we're jumping back to the beginning of the
list. So חורש choreish and זורע zoreya is a כל שהוא. kol
shehu. המלקט עצים, hamelaket eitzim, now if you're gathering the sticks off
of the ground, presumably this is not clear if you're doing this
that you're picking them from the tree, so it's קוצר kotzeir or
you're gathering them from the ground and then it's מעמר. me'ameir. Let's
say, let's bracket קוצר kotzeir for a moment, let's just say it's
gathering and מעמר. me'ameir. What's the minimum amount? אם לתקן כל שהן,
im l'takein kol shehein, if you're doing it to fix the ground
because you now want to plant on the ground, so then it's
a type of a חורש. choreish. So the gathering of the sticks
is not, look, the first thing, if you're doing it to clear
off the ground, we define it as an act of חורש choreish
and חורש choreish we said is a כל שהוא. kol shehu. Okay,
so אם להסיק, im l'haseik, if it is to use it for
firewood, then it's more like מעמר, me'ameir, it's for the sake of
the sticks and it's the מלאכה melacha of gathering. Then gathering, then
that's not כל שהוא, kol shehu, that's the minimum amount that has
a function: כדי לבשל ביצה קלה, kedei l'vashel beitza kalla, the amount
to cook a light egg, which we said meant like a chicken's
egg and to cook the size of the גרוגרת gogeret and to
make it fried or whatever, scrambled. המלקט עשבין, hamelaket asavin, now you're
gathering grass. Same point. אם לתקן כל שהוא, im l'takein kol shehu,
if it is to fix the ground so it's more able to
be planted or for things to grow better, then it's the smallest
amount. חורש choreish and זורע zoreya are כל שהוא. kol shehu. אם
לבהמה, im l'beheima, if it's to feed your animal, כמלא פי הגדי,
k'mlo pi hagdi, it's to feed the, then we go by the
amount that is the minimum amount that an animal would eat that
eats grass and that would be the minimum amount that fits in
the mouth of a goat. So again, what is the מלאכה melacha.
if you're not fixing the ground? It could either be מעמר me'ameir
gathering or it could be, by grass sounds more like you're actually
cutting the grass, not just picking it off the ground, it could
actually be קוצר kotzeir and then it would go by a minimum
amount of use, not a כל שהוא, kol shehu, it would actually
have a higher minimum. Now by the way I should make a
mention, you might have, of this little תוספות: Tosafot אם לבהמה כמלא
פי הגדי ואם להסיק. im l'beheima k'mlo pi hagdi v'im l'haseik. תוספות
Tosafot says פירוש שאינם ראוים לאכילה, peirush she'einam reuyim l'achila,
meaning when it says if it's for this, if it's for this,
it means if it can't be used for one and can only
be used for the other. Because תוספות Tosafot reminds us of a
גמרא Gemara. that says that the minimum שיעור shiur it goes by,
it doesn't go by what you subjectively are intending, it goes by
objectively what the minimum could be used for. Okay, let's see more
of that in the גמרא. Gemara Let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says: למאי חזי? l'mai chazi? So the גמרא Gemara says a little
hole, what can you use it for? חזי לביזרא דקרא, chazi l'bizra
d'kara, like a little one seed of a gourd, דכוותיה גבי משכן,
d'chavatei gabi Mishkan,
just like we had to defend כל שהוא kol shehu by בונה,
we have to defend כל שהוא kol shehu here as well. As
again as תוספות Tosafot, says, if it was any other שיעור shiur
we wouldn't have to defend it. But since it's כל שהוא kol
shehu which means no minimum, we have to find a parallel to
that in the משכן. Mishkan? So what did they do in the
משכן? Mishkan שכן ראויה לקלח אחד של סממנין, shekein reu'ya l'kelach echad
shel samanim, when they had to plant one plant to get the
vegetable thing that they were going to use for dye, even one
hole and one seed would have been enough. המנכש והמקרסם והמזרד, hamenakesh
vehameraksem vehamizared, תנו רבנן: tano rabanan: התולש אושים, hatoleish ushim,
if somebody pulls out like crabgrass or whatever אושים ushim are, המזרד
זרדים hamizared zeradim or cuts off branches, אם לאכילה, im l'achila, yeah
this is what the earlier תוספות Tosafot was going on that I
read to you, if it's for eating, so it's basically like קוצר,
kotzeir, then it's כגרוגרת, k'grogert, then it's the size of a
pressed fig. That is the minimum amount for eating. אם לבהמה, im
l'beheima, if it's to feed to an animal, כמלא פי הגדי, k'mlo
pi hagdi, then it doesn't go by human food measure, it goes
by animal measure which is the mouth of a goat. And here's
where תוספות Tosafoses said that since it's all the same מלאכה, melacha
right, it's the מלאכה melacha, of קוצר, kotzeir, so to determine what
is the minimum, it doesn't go by subjectively what you want to
use it for, it goes by objectively what is the minimum. So
when it says if for this, if for that, it doesn't mean
what's in your mind, it means if it's fit for this. If
it's fit for human food, it goes by גרוגרת. grogert. If it's
only fit for animal food, it goes by מלא פי הגדי. mlo
pi hagdi. That's how תוספות Tosafos is reading it to reconcile it
with other גמרות. Gemaras. אם להסיק, im l'haseik, if it's not fit
for any food and can only be used for firewood, כדי לבשל
ביצה קלה, kedei l'vashel beitza kalla, the amount to cook an egg.
אם ליפות את הקרקע, im l'yafote et hakarka, if you're doing it
to make the ground more able to be planted or for things
to grow, so it's a type of
חורש choreish or קוצר, kotzeir, then... growth of plants is a כל
שהוא. kol shehu. So if it is—if you're doing it for food
or for firewood, it goes by those minimum amounts. But if you're
doing it to make the thing grow better, then it goes by
a כל שהוא. kol shehu. Now there's a very critical question the
גמרא Gemara asks here, which has huge implications for הלכות שבת. Hilchos
Shabbos. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara, says: אטו,
Atu, one minute, says the גמרא, Gemara כולהו לא ליפויי את הקרקע
נינהו? koolhoo lo leyapooyei et hakarka ninhu? All of these things, aren't
they done to make the ground better? Now the way רש״י Rashi
and others explain this is it doesn't mean they're intending to make
the ground better, but the גמרא Gemara says it's having that effect.
What do you mean? Here I am, I am cutting off wood
to use as firewood. But it just happens to be that I'm
pruning the tree, and it's making the tree grow better. So even
if I don't have a minimum for the חיוב chiyuv of קוצר
kotzer because it's not enough for firewood, I had a minimum, I
had a כל שהוא, kol shehu, and I encouraged the growth of
a tree. Why isn't it זורע zoreia or חורש choreish which goes
by a כל שהוא kol shehu since in practice I have done
that act, even if that wasn't what I was—my focus was? So
the גמרא Gemara says, let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabba veRav Yosef de'amri tarveihu, Rabba and
Rav Yosef both say: באגם שנו, be'agam shano, we're talking you did
it in a swamp where nobody cares about what grows in a
swamp, nothing is fit to be grown, and therefore when you pull
out the weeds, you're not preparing the ground for growing anything. So
it's not חורש, choreish, it's not preparing the ground; you're doing it
in a swamp. אוקימתא. Okimta. So the גמרא Gemara says: אביי אמר,
Abaye amar, Abaye says: אפילו תימא בשדה דלאו אגם. afilu teima besadeh
delav agam.
No, even if it's not a swamp, you're doing it in a
field, and by pulling out the grass, even though you're thinking only
about feeding your goat, in practice you are making the ground more
able to be used. So why aren't you חייב chayav for חורש?
choreish? So, כגון דלא קא מכוין, kegon delo ka michavein, like you're
not intending, like you're not interested in—you're not thinking about plants, you're
only interested in feeding your goat. So the גמרא Gemara says: one
minute, ואביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו, va'Abaye veRava de'amri tarveihu, Abaye and Rava
both say: מודה רבי שמעון בפסיק רישא ולא ימות? modeh Rabbi Shimon
bepsik reisha velo yamut? Rabbi Shimon agrees if it's a פסיק רישא,
psik reisha, if it is
a—definitely—like cutting off the head, you can't say I wasn't intending for
the chicken to die when I cut off the head. So can
you cut off a head and it won't die? So here too,
I don't care that you weren't intending to make the ground more
plantable. You cut the grass, and therefore you had—you did that. It
was definitely going to happen, it was going to make it more
able to be planted. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא צריכא דקעביד
בארעא דחבריה. lo tzericha deka'avid be'ara dechavrei. The case is that you're
doing it in your friend's field, and presumably a friend you don't
really—you're not—you don't really care too much about, so it's for you—you
don't care whether you're helping him or not, it's not helping you
to make it—you know, you're not benefiting from it. So what? So
look at רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi says, בארעא דחבריה be'ara dechavrei right
before the משנה: Mishnah לא איכפת ליה ליפויי. lo ikhpat lei leyapooyei.
You have no concern about making his field better, that's not your
interest. Now this leads to a huge category of הלכה halacha which
is critical in הלכות שבת, Hilchos Shabbos, which is called פסיק רישא
דלא ניחא ליה psik reisha delo nicha lei or פסיק רישא דלא
איכפת ליה. psik reisha delo ikhpat lei. You're not intending for something
to happen, it will definitely happen, but it doesn't matter; you have
no interest in it. It's completely not a matter of your concern.
לא ניחא Lo nicha means you actively don't want it; לא איכפת
lo ikhpat means you have—it's not a matter of concern either way.
Here, it's not like you actively don't want it, it's just לא
איכפת, lo ikhpat, not a matter of concern. And לא איכפת lo
ikhpat is for all intents and purposes good enough, it's no difference
between לא איכפת lo ikhpat and לא ניחא ליה. lo nicha lei.
And this is huge, because basically what we say is פסיק רישא
דלא איכפת ליה psik reisha delo ikhpat lei is only rabbinically forbidden.
And therefore under certain circumstances when there's צורך tzorech or whatever, you
combine it with another דרבנן derabbanan or this or that, it actually
will be allowed. Actually, this big תוספות, Tosfos לא צריכא, lo tzericha,
quotes a position of the ערוך Aruch that even says פסיק רישא
דלא איכפת ליה psik reisha delo ikhpat lei is מותר
לכתחילה.
mutar
l'chatchila.
Wow. So that like gets תוספות Tosfos very excited, you know, in
sort of like reacting to that very strongly. But certainly we rule
that פסיק רישא דלא איכפת ליה psik reisha delo ikhpat lei is
only דרבנן. derabbanan. There is no גמרא Gemara that says that. The
whole גמרא Gemara, that that is hinged on, which is like huge,
like half of the things we allow בשעת הצורך besha'at hatzorech on
שבת Shabbos is because it's a פסיק רישא דלא איכפת ליה, psik
reisha delo ikhpat lei, you know, anyway, it's all based on this
answer בארעא דחבריה. be'ara dechavrei. Yes, it'll definitely happen, but you're not
interested in it, so it becomes a פסיק רישא דלא איכפת ליה.
psik reisha delo ikhpat lei. Now, now I should note that there
are some ראשונים Rishonim, that reject that conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara
meaning the ריטב״א Ritva asks a reductio ad absurdum. The ריטב״א Ritva
says, let's say I want to give my cows some exercise. So
to give my cows some exercise, I attach a plow to them,
and I go and I plow your field. Okay, so because, you
know, that'll give—train 'em, it'll be some good exercise for them. Okay,
so am I going to be פטור patur because it's a פסיק
רישא דלא איכפת ליה psik reisha delo ikhpat lei because I don't
really care if your field is plowed? So he thinks that's completely
absurd, and he actually says that the גמרא Gemara only is using
this because it's a כל שהוא. kol shehu. Remember, the whole question
of the גמרא Gemara is why do you have to do the
amount that will fit in the mouth of a goat that would
be a גרוגרת, grogeres, even a כל שהוא kol shehu should be
חייב. chayav. So he says when you're dealing with something so trivial
as a כל שהוא, kol shehu, then you could say if it's
לא איכפת ליה, lo ichpas lei, then it's like the act has
no significance. But that the לא איכפת ליה lo ichpas lei works
together with the fact that you did something tiny, you did something
that was a כל שהוא. kol shehu. Generally, he says there's no
such category like this. So this huge category on שבת Shabbos that
we have, which happens all the time, like a פסיק רישא דלא
איכפת ליה, psik reisha d'lo ichpas lei, he actually would say does
not exist. And actually I don't care what you want or you
don't want, if it's a פסיק רישא, psik reisha, you're חייב. chayav.
Okay, so but this is, that's the ריטב"א. Ritva. We do not
פסקן pasken that way. Okay. Take a deep breath. Okay. But that's
like huge, you know. And now I want to say one other
thing about that, which is is that the question everybody asks is
why is a פסיק רישא דלא איכפת ליה, psik reisha d'lo ichpas
lei, why is that different than a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha
she'eino tzricha l'gufa? Classic מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufa
is I'm digging a hole, I'm only interested in the dirt, but
incidentally I'm digging the hole, which is also type of חורש choresh
or בונה. And the גמרא Gemara calls that מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה.
melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufa. Why not call that פסיק רישא, psik reisha,
the לא איכפת ליה? lo ichpas lei? I'm digging a hole, I'm
interested in the dirt, it happens incidentally that the hole is dug,
that's אינו מתכוין, eino mitkavein, I'm not intending, but פסיק רישא psik
reisha it'll definitely happen, and לא איכפת ליה, lo ichpas lei, I'm
not interested in it. So why, how is that different than מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה? melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufa? So look at one of
the smallest תוספות you'll ever find, which is very critical, בארעא דחבריה,
b'ara d'chavrei, very bottom of the page, פירוש דהוה מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה. peirush de-havei melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufa. So תוספות actually says that
there isn't a difference, they're the exact same, they are the exact
same. Okay. But it doesn't really work in some ראשונים, for example,
the רמב"ם says מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufa you're
חייב, chayav, and he says פסיק רישא דלא איכפת ליה psik reisha
d'lo ichpas lei you're פטור. pattur. So that is a separate question.
There, his question you're doing A, B is resulting, you're not intending
B but it will definitely happen, and you don't care about B.
That example could be what we just called פסיק רישא דלא איכפת
ליה psik reisha d'lo ichpas lei could be called מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה, melacha she'eino tzricha l'gufa, raises the question are they the same
or different. But more important than that for us, as I said,
is that this creates a critical category that at least says at
least it's not אסור דאורייתא, assur d'Oraisa, even when it's a פסיק
רישא psik reisha if you're not interested in the result, okay, and
that really is never explicit in the גמרא Gemara and it all
really hinges on this this גמרא Gemara is one of the key
גמרות Gemaras for that purpose. Right. Did you have a question? No.
Okay. Now we move on. Okay. הכותב שתי אותיות.
Hakosev shetei
osiyos. Somebody writes two letters. בין בימינו בין בשמאלו. Bein b'yimino bein
b'smolo. Now you might remember there was a משנה Mishnah earlier about
carrying whether in your right or left hand, and that wasn't enough
of a שינוי. shinui. Problem here is writing in your left hand,
except for the lefties among us like me, but anyway why is
that considered a normal way of writing if you're writing with your
bad hand? So we'll get back to that. בין משם אחד בין
משתי שמות, Bein mishem echad bein mishtei shemos, whether literally this is
one name or two names, but in this context it means the
same letter or different letters. So you wrote two letters, whether you
wrote אלף אלף aleph aleph or אלף בית, aleph beis, בין משתי
סמניות, bein mishtei samaniyos, whether you used two different types of ink,
בכל לשון, bechol lashon, and whatever language you wrote, whatever script in
whatever language you wrote in, חייב. chayav. Okay. So basically it's two
letters and the other details is regardless of the other details. אמר
רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, לא חייבו שתי אותיות אלא משום רושם.
lo chivu shetei osiyos ella mishum roshem. The reason two letters is
חייב chayav it's not a whole word, it's not for כותב, koseiv,
it's for רושם, roshem, marking. Now what does that mean? He means
that you would have beams, you know, in the משכן Mishkan and
you would basically put, insert slot A, you know, peg A into
slot A. So you'd write an אלף aleph on one beam and
an אלף aleph on the other beam to know they went together,
and then a בית beis and a בית beis and whatever. So
you'd use two letters to combine like things. So he says it's
not about writing a word that makes sense in a language. So
for him it's the מלאכה melacha is less כותב koseiv and it's
more רושם. roshem. The significance for that is it doesn't even have
to be a letter. He says if you made a triangle and
a triangle or something like that, some type of a symbol that
serves some purpose, that's really what it is and it's not כותב.
koseiv.
What? You still need two of them. You still presumably need two,
right, because that's how they did it in the משכן and that's
what he says, שכך כותבין על קרשי המשכן, shekach kosvin al karashei
haMishkan,
that's what you would write on the beams, לידע איזו בן זוגו,
leida eizo ben zugo, to know which one matches which. אמר רבי
יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, מצינו שם קטן משם גדול. matzinu shem katan
mishem gadol.
We have found that you can write a small name out of
a large name. שם משמעון. Shem mishimon.
You're writing the word שמעון Shimon and instead you stopped at שם.
Shem. או משמואל. Or mishmuel. You were writing שמואל and you stopped
at שם. Shem. נח מנחור. Noach minachor. דן מדניאל. Dan midaniyel. גד
מגדיאל. Gad migadiyel. So okay, so that was all very interesting. What
was the point of that? So the גמרא Gemara will see what
his point is, but it's basically even if you're intending to do
a bigger מלאכה and you stopped at two letters, you're also חייב.
chayav. Okay, so not just two letters as that was your entire
intent, but even if you were incomplete because those two letters have
significance. It seems like though if the two letters did not have
significance, couldn't be read, you wrote, I don't know what would be
two letters that couldn't be
read, דלת אלף daled aleph or something unless you're writing in Aramaic.
Anyway, but, so, so two letters that themselves didn't mean anything in
the middle of a word... word, that would not, but if it's
incomplete then it does mean something you are חייב. chayav. That seems
to be what he is saying, adding that idea of not yet
being complete. Yes, Charlie.
So in Hebrew, you need two letters to make any word, but
in English or Chinese
there are one
character.
That's a good question. That's a good question. We'll see more about
that about because there are times where something the גמרא Gemara discusses
like if you made something that was a symbol that meant something
even with one letter, like, you know, an אלף aleph with a
thing which really meant the number one or something like that, you
could be חייב chayav even with less than two letters. So we'll
get back to that.
Let's, yeah. He gives four examples.
Oh, that's a good question. I don't know. I do know that
it's interesting that two of the four examples you had a, it's
really the word you wrote was not completely the same because דלת
נון, dalet nun, the נון nun in the middle of דניאל Daniel
is a middle נון nun and the normal נון nun is an
end נון nun and the same with the מם mem is middle
versus an end מם. mem. The גמרא Gemara. will discuss it, but
it's a good question. I don't know why he made the point
of those four examples. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara גמרא Gemara first
focuses on right and left. בשלמא על ימין לחייב, Bishlama al yamin
lachayiv, I understand you're חייב chayiv with your right hand משום דדרך
כתיבה בכך, mishum d'derech ketiva bekach, that's how you normally write. אלא
שמאל מאי, Ela smola mai, why by your left hand? הא אין
דרך כתיבה בכך, Ha ein derech ketiva bekach, you don't normally write
with your left hand. אמר רבי ירמיה דכולי עלמא באטר יד שנו,
Amar Rabbi Yirmeya d'chulei alma b'itir yad shana, we're talking about a
lefty. It means right or left depending on which is your strong
hand. So the גמרא Gemara says, or maybe it says the whole
משנה Mishnah is talking about a lefty. So then the גמרא Gemara
says if that's true, והוי שמאל דידיה כימין דכולי עלמא, vehavei smol
didei k'yamin d'chulei alma, his left would be like other people's right.
והשמאל חייב והימין לא לחייב. V'asmol chayiv v'yamin lo lachayiv. So again,
he didn't want to read the משנה Mishnah too talking about two
people. If the whole משנה Mishnah is about a lefty, so be
חייב chayiv for your left hand and exempt for your right hand.
אלא אמר אביי בשולט בשתי ידיו. Ela amar Abaye bisholeit bishtei yadav.
The משנה Mishnah. is talking about somebody who's ambidextrous. Okay, now that's
quite funny because again, the משנה Mishnah, is trying to tell you
this big חידוש chiddush of left and we're limiting this משנה Mishna.
radically. But it's interesting that that shows the גמרא Gemara really wants
to, you know, say that things that are really unusual, כלאחר יד,
k'lachar yad, שינוי, shinui, etc., are פטור patur even though the משנה
Mishna seemed to have a broader definition of what's the norm. רב
יעקב בריה דבת יעקב אמר הא מני רבי יוסי. Rav Yaakov brei
d'bas Yaakov amar haman Rabbi Yose. This is actually רבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yose. דאמר לא חייבו שתי אותיות אלא משום רושם. D'amar lo chiyvo
shtei otiyot ela mishum roshem. It's not about writing, it's about marking.
So marking, if you were making a mark, you could make a
mark with your weak hand, it doesn't have to be a nice
letter. You don't write, you don't actually write script with your other,
with your weak hand, but you could make simple marks and therefore
it's considered דרך derech if it's fundamentally about marking and not about
writing. So the גמרא Gemara says, והמדסיפא רבי יוסי היא רישא לאו
רבי יוסי. v'hamidei seifa Rabbi Yose hi reisha lav Rabbi Yose. One
minute, if the end is רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, the beginning is
not רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is only
introduced later. כולה רבי יוסי, Kulei Rabbi Yose, fine, it's all רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. It starts with saying this and then at the
end, you know, to say because according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
it's really not about כותב. koseiv. But that is interesting that if
you emphasize more marking than writing, then what hand is normal becomes
very different. אמר רב יהודה מתנינו. Amar Rav Yehuda matninu. Now we
get to רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda idea about even if it's an
incomplete name, once it's two letters that mean something, you're חייב. chayav.
So the גמרא Gemara noted, and this might answer your question about
why he gave all the examples, that all the examples רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda gave, the two letters that you wrote were different letters.
And in the beginning of the משנה Mishna we emphasized even the
same letter. So the גמרא Gemara wants to focus on that. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא רב יהודה שתי אותיות והן שתי שמות
הוא דמחייב. ela Rav Yehuda shtei otiyot v'hein shtei shemot hu d'mechayiv.
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda only חייב chayav if it's two letters and
they're שמות shemot meaning different letters. שתי אותיות והן שם אחד, Shtei
otiyot v'hein shem echad, two letters that were the same letter, לא
מחייב, lo mechayiv, he wouldn't, because why didn't he give an example
of the same letter? והתניא, Vehatanya, and we taught in a ברייתא
Baraisa that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says even the same letter. And
now we're going to see a ברייתא Baraisa that will be much
bigger than our משנה. Mishnah Okay, it says ועשה אחת. v'asa achat.
It says the פסוק pasuk is ועשה מאחת מהנה, v'asa me'achat mehena,
if a person sins and does from one of these sins. So
the
משנה, the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halakha emphasizes the extra מםs. mem It
could have said ועשה אחת. v'asa achat. Why מאחת מהנה? me'achat mehena?
So אחת, achat, one means a whole מלאכה. יכול עד שיכתוב כל
השם ועד שיארוג כל הבגד, Yachol ad sheyichtov kol hashem v'ad sheyereg
kol habeged, maybe only if you've written the entire name
or you've woven the entire garment. ועד שיעשה כל הנפה, V'ad sheya'aseh
kol hanafa, or let's say you're making a wicker basket, until you
make the entire basket. תלמוד לומר מאחת, Talmud lomar me'achat, even partial,
even if you didn't complete the whole thing. אם מאחת, Im me'achat,
if it's partial, יכול אפילו לא כתב אלא אות אחת, yachol afilu
lo katav ela ot achat, maybe even just one letter? Who, right?
ולא ארג אלא חוט אחד, V'lo arag ela chut echad, you only
wove one string. We normally say two strings. ולא עשה אלא בית
אחד בנפה, V'lo asa ela bayit echad banafa, you only made one
type of a box, you know, when you weave, they sort of
make boxes out of the, you know, out of the wicker. So
maybe if you only did one and not two, maybe there's no
minimum, it's מאחת. me'achat. תלמוד לומר אחת. Talmud lomar achat. So it
says one, it has to be complete. So but not fully complete.
הא כיצד, Ha keitzad, how do you reconcile? Is it one or
is it part of one? אינו חייב עד שיכתוב שם קטן משם
גדול. Eino chayav ad sheyichtov shem katan mishem gadol. It has to
at least be some minimum significance in the size that it is.
Like a small name out of a big name. שם משמעון ומשמואל
נח מנחור דן מדניאל גד מגדיאל. Shem mishimon umishmuel Noach minachor Dan
midaniel Gad migadiel. Okay, so yes, it doesn't have to be the
whole name you... intending but it has to actually be some type
of a name.
So that's what he says. What?
Even for two.
Even for two letters.
Two letters that are just like random.
According to this, if they were two random letters, no, they would
have to actually make some sense, some meaning, it would have to
actually be some name. And actually it even gives an example of
two different letters. So now we're going to continue. רבי יהודה אומר
אפילו כתב אלא שתי אותיות שהן שם אחד חייב. Rabbi Yehuda omer
afilu katav ela shtei otiyot shehen shem echad chayav. Even if it's
the same letter, כגון סס תת רר גג חח. k'gon sas, tat,
rar, gag, chach. So all of those are actually words, so he's
not denying that it has to be a word, but he is
saying that it can even be the same letter. It's quite interesting
the opinion that it has to be different letters. Once it's a
word, who cares? So that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. Yes
it has to be a word, doesn't it have to be the
full word, the full word you were intending, but even the same
letter. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, said רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi,
וכי משום כותב הוא חייב? v'chi mishum kotev hu chayav? One minute.
Why are you driving yourself crazy, same letter, different letter, is it
a word, is it not a word? It's not because of writing
like script, אלא ולא הוא חייב אלא משום רושם. ela v'lo hu
chayav ela mishum roshem. It's about making a symbol, שכן רושמים על
קרשי המשכן לדעת איזו היא בן זוגה, sheken roshmim al karshei HaMishkan
lada'at eizo hi ben zugah, to know which is the pair for
the beams. ולפיכך שרט שריטה אחת על שני נסרים או שתי שריטות
על נסר אחד. u'lefikach sarat srita achat al shenei nesarim o shtei
sritot al neser echad. If you made one line over two, you
know, two beams, by making one line I guess the lines can,
you can match up the edge of one to the beginning of
the next, or two separate lines on two separate beams, even if
they're not letters, but they're symbols to tell you they go together,
או שתי שריטות על נסר אחד, o shtei sritot al neser echad,
or even if it's on one beam, which is interesting, because then
it's like not even physically able doing the function of matching things
up, doesn't matter, two separate symbols, חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav. So
for him he says I don't know what's driving you crazy חח
רר אלף בית, chach, rar, alef, beit, different letter, same letters, word,
it's not about words, any symbol, any two symbols, you're חייב. chayav.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, ועשה
אחת, v'asa achat, and going back to the פסוק, pasuk, you do
one means a whole. יכול עד שיכתוב את כל השם, yachol ad
sheyichtov et kol hashem, maybe only the whole word, like we said
before, עד שיארג כל הבגד עד שיעשה כל הקופה, ad sheyearog kol
habeged ad sheya'aseh kol hakupa, or the whole garment or the whole
basket, תלמוד לומר מאחת, talmud lomar mei'achat, partial. אם מאחת, im mei'achat,
if from, יכול אפילו לא כתב אלא אות אחת, yachol afilu lo
katav ela ot achat, בלא אריג אלא חוט אחד ואפילו לא עשה
אלא בית אחד בקופה, b'lo arig ela chut echad v'afilu lo asa
ela bayit echad bakupa,
exactly like we said before, maybe only one string, one letter, etc.
תלמוד לומר אחת, talmud lomar achat, a full. הכיצד? haikeitzad? אינו חייב
עד שיעשה מלאכה שכיוצא בה מתקיימת. eino chayav ad sheya'aseh melacha shekayotzei
bah mitkayemet.
It has to be a מלאכה that similar to it lasts. And
this is what I said before about the מתקיימת mitkayemet in the
משנה. מתקיימת mitkayemet here could not mean like you didn't write with
disappearing ink, right? That it's that, that it's permanent. That's not, we're
not discussing permanent or impermanent, we're discussing how much did you do.
So מתקיימת mitkayemet here means that you would be considered complete, you
would, you have to do a minimum amount that in some circumstances
you could say you're done and you would leave it that way.
Okay? So anything that would be if you wrote something that would
be incomplete, two letters that don't go together, Z X or something
like that, okay? So that's not a thing of מתקיימת, mitkayemet, there's
nothing, there's nothing of substance there that it's considered done or something
that you would leave that way because obviously it's incomplete. So it
means anything that is complete. So it's not clear how is he
arguing with what was said before. Right, before we also said any
two letters, you know, have, that make up a word. So the
גמרא Gemara will discuss how he's saying something different. Yes.
Is there these הצלה Hatzalah pens for שבת? Shabbos? Like this disappearing
ink kind of thing? Yeah. Okay. It seems like
that
would
be another part of מתקיים, mitkayem, but that's not what we mean
here by מתקיים. mitkayem. Certainly you're פטור patur if it's imper-, if
it, if it's impermanent, you're definitely פטור, patur, that's a different idea
of מתקיים. mitkayem. But here מתקיים mitkayem means, means like something complete
as opposed to incomplete. Yes, מתקיים, mitkayem, right, to be חייב chayav
it needs to be both permanent, permanent question of how permanent, a
day, a week, or whatever, but some degree of permanence and some
degree of completeness. Okay? רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, so רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, ועשה אחת ועשה הנה. v'asa achat v'asa henna.
So going back to this דרשה, drasha, but now emphasizing something different.
פעמים שחייב אחת על כולן, pa'amim shechayav achat al kulan, sometimes you
get one קרבן korban for doing multiple מלאכות. melachot, You might remember
this from way, way earlier. ופעמים שחייב על כל אחת ואחת. u'fa'amim
shechayav al kol achat v'achat. And sometimes it's הנה, henna, sometimes it's
אחת, achat, one קרבן korban for multiple transgressions and sometimes it is
a separate קרבן korban for each transgression. Okay, so that's about קרבנות,
korbanot, which is a separate issue. Now we're going to try to
unpack this very big ברייתא. braita. קתני מיהא. katani miha. Of within
all of this, before we try to figure out how everybody is
different, one of the things we teach in this ברייתא braita is
רבי יהודה אומר אפילו לא כתב אלא שתי אותיות שהן שם אחד
חייב. Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu lo katav ela shtei otiyot shehen shem
echad chayav. That רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said it doesn't have to
be different letters. He said explicitly before him it was said גד
דן שם. Gad, Dan, Shem. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said even חח
רר תת, chach, rar, tat, even if it's the same letter. So
how come, how come over here in the משנה the examples he
gave were different letters? Now you might just say give me a
break, who cares different letters or same letters. But we see that
it's debated whether different letters or same letters. And if רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda in the ברייתא braita says same letter, why is the
example in the משנה one of different letters?
And right and therefore them so it
says. What's it says? There you go. So it says, if you
don't אפילו כתב שתי אותיות והם שם אחד חייב. afilu katav shtei
otiyot vehem shem echad chayav. לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
הא דידיה הא דרביה, ha didei ha derabbai, once his personal opinion,
one is his rebbe's opinion. דתניא detanya we taught in the ברייתא
beraita רבי יהודה אומר משום רבן גמליאל, Rebbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabban
Gamliel, he says in the name of רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, אפילו
כתב אלא שתי אותיות והן שם אחד חייב, afilu katav ella shtei
otiyot vehen shem echad chayav, oh, even if they're the same letter
twice, you're חייב. chayav. כגון kegon if it makes sense it's a
word, שש תת רר גג חח. sas tat rar gag chach. Okay.
So that's answer point number one. There are two opinions out there
that do they have to a everybody seems to say it has
to make a word, does it have to be same letter or
different letters, that is a debate between רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda in
the name of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel who says same letter and
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda himself who would say different letters. Again, I
don't know why you should only be חייב chayav if it's different
letters. You did something of minimum significance, you wrote a word, שש,
sas, let's say you were intending to write a word, why that
should not be enough, I really don't know. But that is debate
number one, it has to be a word, does it have to
be different letters? Now we get back to the other opinions in
this ברייתא. beraita. רבי שמעון היינו תנא קמא. Rebbi Shimon hainu tanna
kamma. Now wait a minute, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon remember he went
back to the whole דרשה drasha again and he said ועשה אחת
ve’asah achat etc. and he said it has to be a minimum
amount that you would leave that way. Isn't that exactly what we
just said? Maybe two letters, maybe one letter,
maybe same letter, maybe different letters, but in the end we just
said both of the opinions already. So וכי תימא vechi teima אלף
אלף alef alef דאזרח de’azrach איכא בינייהו. ika beinihayu. Maybe the question
is he would go so far to say two
letters even if they didn't make sense together. Meaning until now we've
said different letters or same letters but in the end it was
a word. Maybe רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would say two letters even
if it wasn't a word, like you wrote a partial word of
something that was אזרח, azrach, which is a word in the תורה
Torah in ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. And right now the two אלף alef don't
mean anything by themselves. דתנא קמא סבר detanna kamma savar אלף אלף
alef alef דאזרח de’azrach לא מיחייב, lo mechayev, you're not חייב chayav
for that. Even if you're חייב chayav for two letters, two of
the same letters it's only when it makes a word.
רבי שמעון סבר Rebbi Shimon savar כיון דאיתא בגלטורי בעלמא, keivan de’ita
begalturei be’alma, since it exists in some גלטורי galturei which רש"י says
is like a קמיע, kameia, sometimes you use an אלף אלף alef
alef for a קמיע. kameia. So חייב, chayav, you are חייב. chayav.
Okay. So maybe here's what they're debating. The first two opinions said
it had to be a word, and what was debated is same
letters or different letters. Okay. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is coming along
and saying even if it's not a word, even if it's some
type of two letters that is used in some context even non-word
context like you would use it in some type of a קמיע,
kameia, that would be enough. And maybe even the same letter and
even if it's everything, it's a) it's the same letter, b) it's
not a word, you could still be חייב chayav if it had
some type of a use. Maybe that's the debate.
So the גמרא Gemara, says one minute, למימרא, lemeimra, that would say
דרבי שמעון לחומרא, deRebbi Shimon lechumra, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is being
strict when it comes to minimum amounts. והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in
the ברייתא beraita הקודח כל שהוא חייב, hakodeach kol shehu chayav, right
if you make a small hole in a wall like for a
nail, you're
חייב. chayav. המגרר כל שהוא חייב, hamegarer kol shehu chayav, you like
you scrape even the smallest amount. המעבד כל שהוא, hame’abed kol shehu,
you work leather even a small amount. הצר בכלי צורה כל שהוא,
hatzar bikli tzurah kol shehu, you make a little decoration in a
vessel that might be מכה בפטיש. All of those is a כל
שהוא. kol shehu. רבי שמעון אומר Rebbi Shimon omer עד שיקדח את
כולו, ad sheyikdach et kulo, עד שיגרר את כולו, ad sheyigrar et
kulo, you have to do the whole object you're working on. עד
שיעבד את כולו, ad sheye’abed et kulo, you have to do the
whole piece of leather. עד שיצור את כולו ad sheyatzur et kulo
until you do the entire decoration on the vessel. So he says
you have to do the full thing, not a partial thing. Now
again, the גמרא, Gemara it's interesting the גמרא Gemara assumes you can
take a debate in one area and apply it to another. But
here it makes a certain degree of sense, because these are different
מלאכות, melachos. and what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying is doing
part of a whole object is not enough. If you're working on
an object not if you're making something. If you're weaving, you don't
have to make the whole garment. But if you're working on something
pre-existing and you're doing some type of a work on it, you
have to finish it, you have to complete what you're doing. So
if that's his idea that you have to do complete,
presumably he by writing he would say the same, partial writing is
not enough. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara assumes that one debate could
be applied to another. So how could he say two אלף alef
is enough?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא רבי שמעון הכי קאמר, ella Rebbi
Shimon hachi ka’amar, here's what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is saying, עד
שיכתוב את השם כולו, ad sheyichtov et hashem kulo, maybe he is
consistent with his other opinion. The same way he says you have
to work the whole piece of leather and engrave the entire vessel,
maybe he says you have to write the whole name you're intending,
not a partial name. But no, the גמרא Gemara says ומי מצית
אמרת הכי, umi mazit amrat hachi, how could you say that? The
whole point was to say even partial. והתניא, vehatanya, the ברייתא beraita
says, רבי שמעון אומר ועשה אחת, Rebbi Shimon omer ve’asah achat, one.
יכול עד שיכתוב את השם כולו, yachol ad sheyichtov et hashem kulo,
right, his whole point was, maybe you would think you have to
write the whole name, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar מאחת, me’achat, even partial.
So you can't say he demands you do the whole name. So
what are we going to say with רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? Elsewhere
he says you have to work the whole piece of leather. Here
in the ברייתא beraita he says even partial, even not the whole
name. So we have to understand a) how it fits with his
So the way we solve the problem is we rewrite the ברייתא.
braisa. So you might think you would have to write the entire
verse, meaning the whole sentence you were intending to write, תלמוד
לומר talmud lomar מאחת me'achas from one. So basically by seriously editing
the ברייתא, braisa, we have רב שמעון Reb Shimon saying something different
and being consistent with his other positions. The same way you have
to work the whole garment, or not consistent but at least he
had a הוה אמינא. havah amina. You have to work the whole
garment, you have to carve the whole vessel. I might think that
you have to even write the whole sentence because one word doesn't
mean anything by itself. So maybe you have to write the whole
sentence
like you have to work the whole piece of leather. תלמוד
לומר talmud lomar מאחת, me'achas, even if you didn't write the whole
sentence, even if you just wrote one word, so that'd be more
lenient. And now תוספות says why do you have to work the
whole piece of leather and not write the whole sentence? And תוספות
says the difference that I alluded to before, if you're making something
out of nothing, you're weaving a garment, you're writing script on a
blank piece of paper, whatever, then you don't have to do the
entirety. If you however are working on a pre-existing thing, like on
an existing piece of leather and you're smoothing it or tanning it,
then what you're doing has less significance, the thing already exists, and
then רב שמעון Reb Shimon says only when you do the entire
thing. So רב שמעון Reb Shimon demands a more complete act, and
in writing though it is sufficient that it's a complete word but
it does not have to be a complete sentence, and in that
way he's much more lenient than the other opinions. Now we end
with
רב יוסי. Reb Yosi. רב יוסי אומר Reb Yosi omer ועשה אחת
ועשה הנה פעמים שחייב אחת על כולם פעמים שחייב על כל אחת
ואחת. ve'asa achas ve'asa hena pe'amim shechayav achas al kulam pe'amim shechayav
al kol achas ve'achas. He's now taking a different tack, he's no
longer talking about what do you call it, about part of a
word, he's talking about קרבנות. korbanos. Sometimes it's אחת, achas, one קרבן,
korban, sometimes it's הנה, hena, multiple קרבנות. korbanos. So
אמר רב יוסי amar Reb Yosi אחת achas what is one?
Did I skip a line? No. אמר רב יוסי בר חנינא amar
Reb Yosi bar Chanina I did, מאי טעמא דרב יוסי, mai ta'ama
d'Reb Yosi, this is רב יוסי בר חנינא Reb Yosi bar Chanina
the אמורא, amora, what's the reason of רב יוסי? Reb Yosi? אחת
achas מאחת, me'achas, it could have said אחת achas and it had
the מ mem from one. הנה hena מהנה, me'hena, it says from
one. So אחת שהיא הנה והנה שהיא אחת achas she'hi hena ve'hena
she'hi achas from and so we and one that is many, many
that is one. So here's how we דרשן darshen all parts of
those words. אחת achas one thing, I would have said a whole
מלאכה, שמעון. Shimon. מאחת me'achas the מ mem tells me שם משמעון,
Shem mi'Shimon, even if it's not the whole name, even if it's
just the שם Shem from שמעון Shimon is enough. הנה hena those
אבות, avos, that tells me that there are separate קרבנות korbanos for
each separate אב. av. מהנה me'hena from those תולדות, toldos, that there's
things that derive from the אבות avos תולדות. toldos. Okay, some more
fundamental principles of שבת. Shabbos. And now the other point, אחת שהיא
הנה achas she'hi hena and the one that is many and many
that is one. So one that is many is זדון שבת ושגג
מלאכות, zadon Shabbos v'shigag melachos, you knew it was שבת Shabbos and
you forgot the מלאכות. melachos, In that case you did one violation
as it were, you broke שבת Shabbos but because each מלאכה counts
separately because you forgot the individual מלאכות, melachos so that's הנה, hena,
that is multiple קרבנות. korbanos. הנה שהיא אחת hena she'hi achas and
there could be multiple which is only one קרבן. korban. שגג שבת,
shiggag Shabbos, you forgot it was שבת Shabbos וזדון מלאכות, v'zadon melachos,
you knew what you did were forbidden on שבת Shabbos but you
forgot it was שבת. Shabbos. Since there even though you did many
מלאכות since it was one forgetting, you forgot it was שבת, Shabbos,
it is only one קרבן. korban. Again this is a totally different
point that we have said, spent a lot of the seventh פרק,
perek, the beginning of the seventh פרק perek focusing on. But what
we have seen for writing is interestingly an approach that it is
רושם, roshem, it's marks. It's not even about letters, I don't care,
same letters, different letters, whatever, right hand, left hand, it's all about
marks. Another approach that it's much more about writing, so specifically your
good, your strong hand, and then and then it doesn't have to
be a full word, what רב שמעון Reb Shimon says it does.
But anyway, it would also even a partial word as long as
the word makes sense. Even if it was partial what you were
intending, it still has to by itself be a word and that's
interesting. Two letters that's part of a word is not considered complete.
It has to actually be a word even if it wasn't everything
you were intending. And then interestingly there's an opinion that even if
it is a word it doesn't count if it's two of the
same letters, which is very strange. Let's just start, we have two
more minutes, let's just start the next discussion which is a little
fun, okay, which is the שם משמעון Shem mi'Shimon and the problem
that שם, Shem, if you're writing the word שמעון Shimon you wrote
it with an open מ, mem, and how could you call that
the word שם Shem if שם Shem is written with a closed
מ? mem? So אמר רב יהודה amar Reb Yehuda מצינו שם קטן
משם גדול. matzinu shem katan mi'shem gadol. גמרא Gemara says מי דמי?
midami? How could you compare those? מ דשם סתום, mem de'Shem satum,
the מ mem of the word שם Shem is closed. מ דשמעון,
mem de'Shimon, if you were writing the word שמעון, Shimon, the מ
mem you would have written would have been פתוח, pasuach, open. So
if you wrote ש"ם shin-mem with an open מ, mem, you didn't
write a whole word yet. So אמר רב חסדא amar Rav Chisda
זאת אומרת סתום ועשאו פתוח כשר. zos omeres satum va'aso pasuach kosher.
You know what? This tells you that if something should have been
closed and you wrote it open, presumably in something where the script
matters like a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, בדיעבד bedi'avad it's okay. So
even writing it with an open מ mem counts as a word
because an open מ mem can work in the in the place
of a closed מ. mem. So גמרא says, is that really true?
complete writing. That's how you write. And here are some הלכות halachos
about how תפילין tefillin and מזוזות mezuzos have to be written. שלא
יכתוב אלפין עיינין, Shelo yichtov alfin ayinin, don't write an אלף alef
and עין, ayin, עיינין אלפין ayinin alfin or an עין ayin and
אלף. alef. Not that they look the same, but because some people
don't do a guttural עין, ayin, they sound the same, so you
might accidentally exchange them. And now the rest have to do with
how they look. ביתין כפין, כפין ביתין, Beisin kafin, kafin beisin, don't
write a בית beis as a כף, kaf, a כף kaf as
a בית. beis. The letters have to be very distinct. Write a
בית beis and כף kaf could look almost the same. גימלין צדין,
צדין גימלין, Gimlin tzadin, tzadin gimlin, don't write a גימל gimel and
צדי, tzadi, גימל gimel like a צדי, tzadi, צדי tzadi like a
גימל. gimel. Those also could look very similar. דלתין רישין, רישין דלתין,
Daltin reishin, reishin daltin, don't write a דלת daled like a ריש,
reish, a ריש reish like a דלת. daled. Right, דלת daled and
ריש reish are very similar, right? It's all about that little thing
that sticks out from the back. הין חיתין, חיתין הין, Hein cheisin,
cheisin hein, don't write a ה hei like a חית ches or
a חית ches like a ה. hei. Also very similar letters. ווין
יודין, יודין ווין, Vavin yodin, yodin vavin, a יוד yud like a
ו vov or vice versa. זיינין נונין, נונין זיינין, Zayinin nunin, nunin
zayinin, a זיין zayin like a נון, nun, a נון nun meaning
a נון סופית, nun sofit, right? So those, that looks very similar
to a זיין zayin or a נון nun like a זיין. zayin.
טיתין פאין, פאין טיתין, Titin pein, pein titin, don't write a טית
tes like a פא pei or a פא pei like a טית.
tes. כפופים פשוטים, Kfufim peshutim, don't write the bent ones straight, meaning
like a כף chaf or a נון nun that should be bent,
don't write it like a נון סופית nun sofit or a כף
סופית chaf sofit where it's straight down. פשוטים כפופים Peshutim kfufim or
the reverse. ממין סמכין, Memin samchin, don't write a מם סופית mem
sofit like a סמך, samach, very similar. סמכין ממין. Samchin memin. סתומים
פתוחים, פתוחים סתומים. Stumim ptuchim, ptuchim stumim. Don't write open things like
a מם mem that's open, closed, or closed thing open. So don't
write an open מם mem like a closed מם mem or a
closed מם mem like an open one. פרשה פתוחה לא יעשנה סתומה.
Parsha ptucha lo ya'asennu stuma. If the פרשה parsha is פתוחה, ptucha,
right, you know how they say in the, in some times you
know in the חומש Chumash it has a פ pei at the
end of a פרשה. parsha. פתוחה Ptucha means it's a blank line
till the end. It's open. Okay. So don't write that סתומה stuma
when it says a ס. samech. That means you leave a blank
space and then you continue the next פרשה parsha on the same
line. That's the difference between פתוחה ptucha and סתומה. stuma. Don't write
a פתוחה ptucha as a סתומה, stuma, סתומה לא יעשנה פתוחה. stuma
lo ya'asennu ptucha. Okay. כתבה כשירה, Ksavah keshirah, let's say you wrote
the normal text like you would write the שירה shirah like, like
you write אז ישיר Az Yashir or you write האזינו Ha'azinu where
you write them like with white spaces between various sections or like
as two columns. או שכתב את השירה כיוצא בה, O shekasav es
hashirah kiyotzei bah, you wrote the שירה shirah like a normal text.
או שכתב שלא בדיו, O shekasav shelo bedyo, you didn't use דיו.
dyo. או שכתב את האזכרות בזהב, O shekasav es ha'azkaros bezahav, you
thought you're going to be fancy, you wrote God's name in gold.
הרי אלו יגנזו. Harei elu yignazu. All of those are פסול ספרי
תורה pasul sifrei torah and they have to be put into גניזה.
genizah. Okay. So basically what do you see? You see that you
can't write a מם mem as an open מם mem as a
closed מם mem and a closed מם mem as an open מם.
mem. So, no, but presumably for a ספר תורה Sefer Torah at
least. So anyway, I'll
leave you with that cliffhanger. So we will find out tomorrow if
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah you can't switch them, why the משנה
assumes that if you did switch them, it's enough to be חייב,
chayav, and we will find out about that tomorrow.